# STEVE CAO

2044 Treewood Lane • San Jose, CA 95132 • (408) 544-0502 • steve.cao7@gmail.com

#### SUMMARY

Research professional with six years of experience in a high throughput services laboratory. Adept at molecular biology wet work and troubleshooting various processes. Experience with developing new lab space, work flow, and Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs). Highly self-driven and flexible with an eagerness to learn new skillsets.

### **SKILLS**

DNA Microarray	QC	Automation	LIMS
Affymetrix Axiom Assay	Affymetrix WT Pico Assay	Beckman Biomek FXp	DNA/RNA Purification
IENCE	·		

## **EXPERIENCE**

#### 2011 - Present

#### Thermo Fisher (formerly Affymetrix)

Santa Clara, CA

Scientist II

- Operate Beckman Coulter FXp liquid handlers to conduct experiments and validate methods
- Troubleshoot Beckman Coulter FXp liquid handlers during experiments
- Train new hires on a range of laboratory procedures and write standard operating procedures (SOPs) for new technology within the group
- Oversee running the largest genome wide association study to date in collaboration with UK Biobank.
- Conduct high throughput genotyping utilizing Affymetrix Axiom microarray technology
- Utilize laboratory information management systems (LIMS) and optimize its usage in lab
- Conduct experiments with Hamilton Nimbus liquid handlers
- Execute quantification and normalization of nucleic acids with PicoGreen technology and also using NanoDrop technology
- Perform PCR, gel electrophoresis, purification, quantification and formulate own buffers and gels
- Prepare RNA for assays using Zymogen kit RNA extractions
- Handle fresh frozen tissue, RNA-later tissues, and FFPE tissue for Affymetrix RNA expression and Affymetrix QuantiGene Plex platforms
- Manage multiple projects simultaneously ranging from sample processing to quality control
- Design new lab space to maximize work flow and efficiency with lean standards in mind

2007 – 2010 University of the Pacific Stockton, CA

Undergraduate Research Associate

- Learned about the properties of spider silk
- Created part of cDNA library from Black Window spiders, Lactrodectus Hesperus
- Isolated cDNAs from cDNA library of Black Window spiders, Lactrodectus Hesperus
- Performed minipreps to purify DNA for sequencing in order to look for homologs
- Ran countless PCR and gel electrophoresis

#### **EDUCATION & HIGHLIGHTS**

# University of the Pacific

Stockton, CA

Bachelor of Science, Biological Sciences (2010)

# Foothill Community Health Center CA

San Jose,

Outreach and translator volunteer (2016-Present)